<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe ansvver to R.H. his booke, entitled, The true guide, &amp;c. Wherein are occasionally declared and proved by Scripture these particular things following: [brace] first, that the baptisme of water is a distinct baptisme from the baptisme of the spirit. ... Sixthly, in what sense some things related in Scripture are not Scripture, with divers other particulars occasionally spoken of. / By R.B. a well-wisher to the truth, and R.H.</title>
            <author>R. B., Well-wisher to the truth.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76289</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B159</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E357_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16628</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860066</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860066</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112173</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76289)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112173)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 57:E357[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe ansvver to R.H. his booke, entitled, The true guide, &amp;c. Wherein are occasionally declared and proved by Scripture these particular things following: [brace] first, that the baptisme of water is a distinct baptisme from the baptisme of the spirit. ... Sixthly, in what sense some things related in Scripture are not Scripture, with divers other particulars occasionally spoken of. / By R.B. a well-wisher to the truth, and R.H.</title>
                  <author>R. B., Well-wisher to the truth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 37, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at his shop at the west end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Hollingworth, Richard. The true guide (Wing H2499).</note>
                  <note>The words "first, that the baptisme .. spoken of." are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 12".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hollingworth, Richard, 1607-1656. --  True guide.</term>
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112173:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112173:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE ANSVVER To R. H. His Booke, ENTITLED, <hi>The True Guide,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Wherein are occaſionally declared and proved by Scripture theſe particular things following:</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That the Baptiſme of water is a diſtinct Baptiſme from the Baptiſme of the ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That the Baptiſme of Water doth not by Scripture ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion ſignifie the Baptiſme of the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>What is ſignified by the Baptiſme of Water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>In whom the true Right of Church-power reſides, and how typified in the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>The State of the Church and Miniſtry in Babylon, typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and myſticall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>In what ſenſe ſome things related in Scripture are not Scripture, with divers other particulars occaſionally ſpoken of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>R. B.</hi> A well-wiſher to the truth, and <hi>R. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 18.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He that is firſt in his owne cauſe ſeemeth juſt, but his neighbour commeth and ſearcheth him.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 30.12, 13, 14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>There is a generation that are pure in their owne eyes, and yet are not waſhed from their filthineſſe.</p>
               <p>Read <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the Weſt end of PAUL<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:112173:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112173:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL men are naturally addicted to take up that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion for the true Religion, which they find to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and allowed in that Nation wherein they are borne; thoſe that are borne in <hi>Turkey</hi> take up the <hi>Mahumetan</hi> Religion, thoſe that are borne in <hi>Rome</hi> the Popiſh Religion, and yet neither of theſe the true Religion and Worſhip of God; ſo that it plainly appeares, that whole States have been deceived in matter of Religion and Worſhip, and what State can be inſtanced, that the Succeſſors haue not in many particulars con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted their Predeceſſors, and both of them cannot be in the right, for the Truth is but one, us God is one; the cauſe of this chiefly is, becauſe men rather take up Religion, then are taken up of it; men commonly take things upon truſt, untried, doing as other of their Neighbours do, even live in men in matters of Religion and Worſhip, more than in God; contrary to that, <hi>Matth. 15.9. Col. 2.20, 22.</hi> moſt men dreame of a worldly Sanctuary ſtill in being, whereas Gods houſe in the time of the Goſpell is Spirituall. The Apoſtacy from the Faith under Antichriſt is a meere Riddle to thouſands, yea, and thouſands that are convinced of that Apoſtacy, confine it to the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Church, and plead a reſtitution from <hi>Luthers</hi> time, but point blanke from Queene <hi>Elizabeths.</hi> And yet we ſee much of that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected of late; and muſt it needs be, there are no Truths left behind ſtill undiſcovered, Prophecying in Sack-cloath? God is not bound to reſtore all Truth at once, nor to a multitude, but even a few, and they perhaps <hi>deſpiſed ones, 1 Cor. 1.27, 28.</hi> even like thoſe <hi>Fiſher-men</hi> which Chriſt choſe. It is well known the decay of Truth was gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all from the Apoſtles times, as may be ſeene, <hi>2 Theſ. 2.3, 7.</hi> and <hi>Rev.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112173:3"/> 8,</hi> and <hi>9. Chapters.</hi> And the reſtitution is likewiſe graduall, as may appeare, <hi>Revel. 14.</hi> and <hi>16. Chapters.</hi> Where we may obſerve the <hi>Truths</hi> increaſe, and <hi>Antichriſts</hi> decreaſe by degrees contemporiſing ſo, that the riſe of the one, is the decay of the other; which being well conſidered, may ſerve to convince many of a too common errour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us; for moſt men, yea, even many Profeſſours are reſolved, as by their practice may appeare, to receive nothing for Truth, but that which hath the ſtampe of a State Approbation. Had ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours lived in the Apoſtles times, the Truth and ſuch would have had little acquaintance, for Chriſt ſaith plainly, <hi>Luke 17.20. The Kingdome of God cometh not with obſervation:</hi> And I ſuppoſe Chriſt will come with as little worldly ſtate and pompe at the reſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Truth from under Antichriſt, as at the firſt publiſhing of it to the Gentile world: <hi>Matth. 12.19.</hi> But becauſe Chriſt hath none of this forme or beauty among men, <hi>Eſay 55.1, 2, 3.</hi> He is deſpiſed, rejected and not eſteemed; the leſſon of bearing the croſſe, <hi>Luke 14.26.27.</hi> is a hard leſſon, and yet true Diſciples learne it; I will only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe two cavets to the Chriſtian Reader, and ſo conclude. The firſt is this, take heed of rejecting <hi>true light,</hi> under a pretence of <hi>reproached new light,</hi> leaſt in ſo doing, thou reject Chriſt. Secondly, take heed of receiving older <hi>new light</hi> from any men whatſoever upon truſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryed by the Word and Spirit, leaſt that curſe light upon thee, <hi>Jer. 17.5. Thus ſaith the Lord, curſed be the man that truſteth in man, and maketh fleſh his arme,</hi> ſuch are ſaid, <hi>to depart from the Lord in their hearts:</hi> If any thing I have written in this enſuing Tract, come in evidence of Truth, receive it, as thoſe <hi>Samaritans, John 4.42. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of Chriſts owne Word,</hi> If any thing I have written, appeare otherwiſe to thee upon tryall, reject it, and ſo will I through Gods grace, any mans Sayings or Writings diſſenting from the Word of Truth: but let thee and I receive and reject in Love, and the God of Peace and Love ſhall be with us, and make us one in Truth alſo in his own time, <hi>Phil. 3.15. Joh. 17.17, 19, 21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:112173:3"/>
            <p>TO ſpeake a word or two, and ſo to let paſſe this Epiſtlers inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives and reproaches, we being frequently uſed to beare them from the Pulpit, can the eaſier beare them from the Preſſe; and we having experience of his fallibility in judgement, ever ſince the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops impoſitions, conceive them to be more prejudiciall to themſelves then to us, they being evident diſcoveries of the bitterneſſe of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit againſt us that differ in judgement from him; but being ſo void of Truth from Scripture to backe them, we ſhall eſteeme of them but as the <hi>Ignis fatuus</hi> of his own braine, for he hath only three quoted Proofes from Scripture, not to make good his reproaches, but to prove two things; namely, that there muſt be Hereſies and falſe Prophets, both which we eaſily grant, having had ſo long experience thereof; for we find that Antichriſtian Spirit to have begun and continued ever ſince the Apoſtles times till this day, and that with no ſmall eſteem in the world: for honour and greatneſſe amongſt men they chiefly hunt after, the Diſciples of Chriſt were infected with it, but durſt not own it before Chriſt, <hi>Mark. 9.33, 34.</hi> for he expreſly forbids it, <hi>Matth. 20.25, 26, 27. Luke 22.25, 26, 27.</hi> This lofty Spirit began in <hi>Diotrephes, 3 John 9.</hi> and ever ſince this Epiſcopall generation have loved and endeavoured to have the preheminence, theſe falſe Prophets are very covetous, <hi>2 Pet. 2.3. 2 Cor. 11.20.</hi> The true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Chriſt were not ſo, <hi>2 Cor. 12.17.</hi> The falſe Prophet, and the Antichriſtian Beaſt aſpire and expire, live and dye together, <hi>1 Joh. 4.1, 3. Rev. 20.10.</hi> They came to ſome height even in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles times, for they raigned like Kings, whereas the Apoſtles, the true ſervants of God, were in diſgrace and reproach, they were at peace, while the true ſervants of God were perſecuted, <hi>1 Cor. 4.8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13.</hi> They could ſwallow down impoſitions from men, <hi>Gal. 6.12.</hi> which the true Servants of Chriſt could not do, and this was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they deſired to make a faire ſhew in the fleſh, and to avoid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, as in the place before quoted appeares, the true ſervants of Chriſt were accuſed of Hereſie, <hi>Acts 24, 14.</hi> yea, accounted Sectaries and ſeditious, <hi>Acts 24.5.</hi> and under that notion of Sectaries, they were every where ſpoken againſt, <hi>Acts 28.22.</hi> and were accuſed of, and charged with many things which could not be proved againſt them, <hi>Acts 24.23.</hi> This I ſay that even as then, ſo now is it the portion of Gods people. But one thing I note in particular, which is his calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niating
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112173:4"/> the maintainers of free-Grace, as if they were the Abetters of carnall liberty. Truly I canot ſee how any that underſtand the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Gods Free Grace aright, can make ſuch concluſions, except Legaliſts or carnall Chriſtians; my reaſon is, becauſe the trueſt and moſt active principle of all holineſſe in converſation, is the right knowledge and experience of Gods Free-Grace and Love, the which knowledge is no acquired thing, as he conceives, but is the free gift of God, <hi>Epheſ. 1.17, 18.</hi> and <hi>Luke 1.77. ſaving knowledge</hi> is there ſaid to ſpring from <hi>the remiſſion of ſins,</hi> and ſo it followes, that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving knowledge is no more acquirable then Salvation it ſelfe, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins: And where as he complaines of thorny objections that indangers the pricking of their fingers, I anſwer him as Jeſus Chriſt did <hi>Saul,</hi> afterwards called <hi>Paul, It is hard for thee to kicke againſt the prickes, Acts 9 5.</hi> ſo it is hard indeed to reſiſt the Spirit of God, whoſe comming is ſaid to be in brightneſſe and clearneſſe of the Truth, to deſtroy all Antichriſtian Tenents, though they were eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med never ſo Orthodoxe before, <hi>2 Theſ. 2.8.</hi> The Lord guide both him and me to ſee the Truth as it is in Jeſus, and there to reſt, and not as it is in any man or men whatſoever, even as <hi>Saint Paul</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, <hi>Be ye followers of me as I am of Chriſt, Epheſ. 5.1.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="pamphlet">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:112173:4"/>
            <head>A Briefe Amſwer to <hi>R. H.</hi> his Book, called, The <hi>TRUE GUIDE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt he ſtiles his Booke the <hi>True Guide,</hi> A ſpeech very Emphaticall, and ſeemes to me a Title too high for any ſinfull Creature either to aſſume to himſelfe, or affixe to his writings: for never did any one of the Apoſtles aſſume it, but it was given only to Jeſus Chriſt, and to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth. Firſt to Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.5. <hi>The faithfull witneſſe:</hi> And take notice of the word <hi>The,</hi> three times in that verſe. Alſo it is given to the Spirit expreſly, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.13. when he, <hi>The Spirit of Truth is come, he ſhall guide you into all Truth. John Baptiſt</hi> indeed was <hi>A burning and a ſhining light, Joh.</hi> 5.35. but Jeſus Chriſt was <hi>the true light, Ioh.</hi> 1.9. and <hi>The way, The truth, and The life. Ioh.</hi> 14.6. But if his Spirit had been infallible, and he had titled his Book <hi>A True Guide,</hi> in ſtead of <hi>The True Guide,</hi> then might his Title have proved Orthodoxe (I hope he will ſuffer his Epiſtlers termes) which now muſt remaine Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodoxe, and muſt of neceſſity be degraded.</p>
            <p>Further, he ſaith, <hi>the weakeſt Chriſt an may be able to diſcerne the true way of the Spirit of God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By <hi>way of the Spirit,</hi> I ſuppoſe <hi>R. H.</hi> chiefly intends the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward way of it, and that eſpecially in the publike Miniſtery, as may appeare in his third diſtinction, Pag. 1. and his ſo oft mentioning of it almoſt in every Page to the end of the Booke, at leaſt it is the chiefe thing in difference betwixt us, and whereupon I ſhall chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſiſt.</p>
            <p>Truly, it is ſtrange to me that <hi>R. H. his Guide</hi> ſhould habilitate
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112173:5"/> 
               <hi>the weakeſt Chriſtian to diſcerne the true way of the Spirit of God,</hi> about the publike Miniſtry, for that he chiefly drives at, whereas the ſtrongeſt Chriſtians indued with far greater light about this point in controverſie, then ever yet <hi>R. H.</hi> ſaw, are at a ſtand about it, witneſſe the ſtrong Controverſie yet on foot, about that point of Miniſtery and Church-Government, even amongſt them of cleareſt light. Which Controverſie was not in the Primitive times after the giving of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. For during the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of thoſe neceſſary members of the Church of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.27. the Apoſtolical Office &amp; Gifts which were infallible, there was no place left for any difference among the Churches in that point, it being a part of the truth of the Goſpell revealed; for if it were not ſo, then by as good reaſon they might queſtion the certainty of the whole Goſpell, as that part of it. Witneſſe likewiſe the flow comming in of the Synods Anſwer to the Parliaments Quaeries.</p>
            <p>It followes, <hi>from all falſe and erronious wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly, <hi>R. H.</hi> muſt needs be indued with the gift of diſcerning of Spirits at leaſt, a gift not given to all in the Primitive Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.10. <hi>To another the working of miracles, to another Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, to another diſcerning of Spirits,</hi> &amp;c. I wonder that we in this Towne living ſo neare him, have reaped no better fruits of it, having divers times both by word and writing, deſired conference with him in a loving way, and could not obtaine it, but were put off with this excuſe, he had a paine in his head, by reaſon of which his memory was weake. Truly, had not his love to us been weaker then that he made ſhew of, and ſeemed earneſtly oft times to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, he would have dealt with us as brethren, and not have given us the firſt fruits of it in a ſcandalous and lying Pamphlet publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed to the world, but would either by word or writing, firſt have taken counſell of the Word and Spirit, in <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.15. <hi>If thy brother treſpaſſe against thee, go tell him his fault betwixt him and thee alone,</hi> &amp;c. which all Chriſtians that underſtand that place (both in Old and New-<hi>England</hi>) confeſſe to be a rule obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, not only betwixt particular Brethren, but by Analogie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Churches themſelves in caſe of difference. But he leaves not only that way, but alſo the <hi>more excellent way of Love,</hi> as the Apoſtle cals it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.31. <hi>But covet earneſtly the beſt gifts, and yet ſhow I vnto you a more excellent way,</hi> compared with 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.1.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112173:5"/> 
               <hi>follow after charity,</hi> (which way of love is not only to be ſought before, but is indeed more excellent then all Ordinances) and likewiſe the Prophets and Apoſtles examples, who never publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed to the world, the grievances or imperfections of the people of God, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Tell it not in Gath, publiſh it not in the ſtreets of Askelon, &amp;c Mica.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Declare it not at Gath,</hi> &amp;c. Yet the Apoſtles in divers of their Epiſtles, had to do with falſe Apoſtles, and with ſcandalous and falſe Brethren.</p>
            <p>But he knowing no <hi>world,</hi> no <hi>Gath,</hi> nor <hi>Askelon</hi> now in being, takes this unbrotherly courſe to render us, that differ in judgement from him, as odious to the world as he can: therefore we may juſtly take up <hi>Davids</hi> complaint, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120. throughout the whole Pſalme, but had he not wronged the Truth as well as us, it had been much the better, and we had been prevented of making this juſt vindication.</p>
            <p>It followes, <hi>By a lover of the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This may be ſo, if it be underſtood of that which he judges Truth, but to love Truth is to love God, for God is Truth; and then if he love him that begat, he alſo loves him that is begotten of him. Alſo if he be a lover of the Truth indeed, then he loves all Truth as well as any, and that for its owne ſake, yea, even thoſe Truths that are againſt him, as well as thoſe that are for him, and is as willing to know it as was Old <hi>Ely,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.17. which made him ſay to <hi>Samuel, what is the thing that the Lord ſaid unto thee, I pray thee hide it not from me, &amp;c.</hi> &amp; to ſubmit to it being known, as he, <hi>v.</hi> 18. <hi>and he ſaid it is the Lord, let him do what ſeemeth him good,</hi> yea, though it put him upon ſuffering, <hi>Revel.</hi> 10.10. Thus far the frontiſpiece.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Text</hi> follows, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14.</p>
            <p>The principall drift of his diſcourſe is about <hi>diſcerning the true way of the Spirit of God,</hi> eſpecially as it concernes the <hi>publike Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry,</hi> as is ſaid before. His third diſtinction in Pag. 1. he divides into two, <hi>(viz)</hi> firſt <hi>inward.</hi> Secondly, <hi>outward</hi> and <hi>Miniſteriall,</hi> which latter is indeed the ſenſe implyed in his third obſervation. <hi>Page</hi> 2. Now had he purpoſed to have been a <hi>True Guide,</hi> he ſhould have ſhewed himſelfe a workeman, as <hi>Paul</hi> counſelled <hi>Timothy,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. by rightly diſtinguiſhing between Miniſters and Miniſtries according to the Word, and not to have begged
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112173:6"/> the queſtion, as it is plaine he doth, he being either unwilling or unable to play upon that ſtring, but would have us take his word for it, as he doth others. Certaine it is he allowes of more Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtries then one, for he himſelfe preaches, and we do not queſtion him for it, but we know not of any Office he hath yet, ſo that his preſent practice warrants a Miniſtry without an Office, according to that <hi>Acts</hi> 8.4. <hi>they that were ſcattered abroad, went every where preaching the Word,</hi> and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10. <hi>as every man hath received the gift, even ſo miniſter the ſame one to another, as good Stewards of of the manifold Grace of God.</hi> And ſo farre I hope others may goe as well as he. But this he will ſay is not the <hi>publike Miniſtery</hi> he ſpeakes of: but what doth <hi>R. H.</hi> thinke makes a <hi>Miniſtery publike?</hi> Is it ſomething in and about it called <hi>Jure divino,</hi> or <hi>Jure humano?</hi> If he ſay the <hi>latter,</hi> then Chriſts Miniſtery and <hi>John Baptiſts</hi> were not <hi>publike,</hi> for they had it not. If he ſay the <hi>former,</hi> then there be many now in <hi>London</hi> and other places, who have it not in his way, which yet have as good, and better teſtimony from the Word for theirs, then he hath for his.</p>
            <p>In his ſecond obſervation, he takes a great deale of paines in quoting a multitude of Scriptures, to prove a thing we eaſily grant, for we have had long experience of being ſeduced, though not ſo long experience as he; if the Lord would be pleaſed to diſcover it to him.</p>
            <p>In his third obſervation, <hi>Page</hi> 3. he ſaith, <hi>the moſt are led by an erronious ſpirit;</hi> now if this be true, as certainly it is, and his Church conſiſting of all men, who are the moſt, ſee how he foyles himſelf, and diſgraceth his Church. The true Church-members are all <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtones,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeakes <hi>(in appearance at leaſt)</hi> now if the Church knew of any one defiled perſon in it, and did not caſt him out, it was her great ſin, and a means of infecting the whole lump, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Your glorying is not good, know you not that a little hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven leaveneth the whole lump?</hi> But he confeſſeth (and we ſhould beleeve the <hi>True Guide) that moſt are led by an erronious ſpirit,</hi> therefore a body deſperately corrupt by his own poſition.</p>
            <p>Further in the ſame Page, he takes the Apoſtles weakeneſſes to ſerve his turne, never diſtinguiſhing betwixt their ſailings in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Practice, and ſo in ſtead of being a <hi>True Guide,</hi> may prove a <hi>falſe</hi> one; eſpecially to weake Chriſtians, for whom is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112173:6"/> ſeemes he chiefly intended his Booke; for they may thinke if the Apoſtles erred, whom ſhould we beleeve? and ſo he may bring a blot upon his <hi>True Guide,</hi> and men may ſay if the Apoſtles erred, why may not <hi>R. H.</hi> erre alſo?</p>
            <p>But I wiſh him how ever it fares with his <hi>True Guide,</hi> to take heed leaſt by opening the Prophets and Apoſtles failings in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Practice, to ſerve his own turne, he make not their Doctrine queſtionable with his, in which they could not erre as they were Apoſtles, and moved by the Holy Ghoſt in execution of their Office. But it followes not, but that another, even a publike Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery may erre, therfore his whatſoever it be, is as queſtionable as any other, though he leaves it unqueſtionable and queſtions all others, making hue and cry after them under the name of ſeducers, if they have not his allowance and run not in his ſtreame. But I deſire him to ſhew us by what right others are bound to have his approbation more, then he theirs; unleſſe he ſtand for ſome mother Church, and would bring other Churches and Aſſemblies under it whether they will or no; truly, I know of no mother Church but that ſpoken of by S. <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 4.26. <hi>Jeruſalem which is above, the mother of us all.</hi> Indeed I read of union, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.9. <hi>My Dove, my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled is but one, ſhe is the only one of her mother;</hi> but of no ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination of Churches, this opinion he knowes is ſomewhat Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh. But let him ſhew us where Chriſt or his Apoſtles conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted any one Church over another Church or Churches, from whence a patterne may be taken for any ſuch preheminence, and he hath done the worke: when he hath alſo proved his true ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (for certainly he muſt goe that way to worke) and alſo his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility of judgement, as he knows the mother Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is forced to do, like an Ape, imitating the Primitive Church, who alone enjoyed (in the time of the Apoſtles, thoſe uſefull and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary members of the Chriſtian Churches) the true way of Goſpell Churches.</p>
            <p>Further, in <hi>Page</hi> 3. he propounds a queſtion, <hi>how the Spirit of Truth may be known from the Spirit of Errour:</hi> his anſwer is, <hi>Gal,</hi> 5.22. <hi>But the fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, long-ſuffering, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe goodneſſe, faith, &amp;c.</hi> Here <hi>R. H.</hi> was at a ſtand, for his old papers did not afford him a particular anſwer to this quaere, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he contents himſelfe with a generall one, for we know that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112173:7"/> he hath been long ſince compiling this modell by the helpe of his old notes, which he made uſe of to this purpoſe. And truly, had he well viewed that Text, it is not a very pertinent place to his purpoſe, ſave only in the generall to diſcover <hi>ſeducers</hi> from a <hi>True Guide,</hi> but rather a <hi>falſe</hi> Chriſtian from a <hi>true</hi> one, and alſo is meant properly of a perſecuting biting, devouring Spirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.15. <hi>But if ye bite and devoure one another, take heed ye be not conſumed one of another.</hi> Or in plaine tearmes, a <hi>Legaliſt</hi> from a <hi>Spirituall</hi> man <hi>ver.</hi> 18. <hi>but if ye are led by the Spirit, ye are not under the Law,</hi> a <hi>loving, peaceable</hi> man, from a <hi>van-glourious, envious</hi> man, <hi>ver.</hi> 22.26. But had he been as well verſed in the Scripture as in his old notes, Saint <hi>John</hi> would have ſufficiently furniſhed him with par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars for that purpoſe, but that he thought it would make againſt him: 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.2, 3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Every Spirit that confeſſeth that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh is of God, and every Spirit that confeſſeth not that Chriſt is come in the fleſh is not of God, and this is that Spirit of Antichriſt whereof you have heard that it ſhould come, and even now already is it in the world,</hi> and ſo <hi>ver</hi> 5. <hi>They are of the world, therefore ſpeak they of the world, and the world heareth them, we are of God, he that knoweth God, heareth us, he that is not of God heareth not us, hereby know we the Spirit of Truth, and the Spirit of Error:</hi> but it may be he hath not heard that place ſo expounded, and had he tooke notice alſo of <hi>Eſay</hi> 57.19. <hi>I create the fuit of the lips, &amp;c.</hi> he ſhould have there read of a <hi>fruit of the lips</hi> as well as of the <hi>fruits of converſation</hi> elſe where, which ſenſe <hi>John</hi> proceeds in, to diſcover ſeducers in the place before quoted. But <hi>R. H.</hi> not being acquainted with it, thought a generall diſcovery might paſſe, but he finds in Scripture that Seducers come in Sheeps cloathing, they ſeem to be holy in their converſation, therefore the <hi>fruit of the lips</hi> ſeeme to be the moſt proper diſtinguiſhing character to know them by, for neither he nor I, can tell when we ſee things done agreeable to the Word that it is a fruit of the Spirit, for all that we can ſee is but a Morall thing: therefore <hi>Paul</hi> when he ſpeakes of the fruits of the fleſh, ſaith, <hi>they are manifeſt, Gal.</hi> 5.19. but he doth not ſay, the <hi>fruits of the Spirit</hi> are manifeſt, <hi>verſe</hi> 22. for they are not ſo eaſily known to us, only the judgement of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which is ſo much wanting in him towards us, ſhould be in us all towards them whoſe actions are according to the Word.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:112173:7"/>
            <p>In <hi>Page</hi> 4. in his foure laſt lines, in applying his Anſwer to a generall Queſtion there propounded, he mentions Chriſts Anſwer to the Diſciples about their commanding fire to come down from Heaven, &amp;c. Chriſt doth indeed as he ſaith, reject their anſwer, and good reaſon for it, though it was not as he ſaith, altogether contrary to the Word written, for they had <hi>Elias</hi> for their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to juſtifie their demand, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 1.10. and ſo they had ſome Scripture to ground their demand upon, but the Diſciples being yet ſomewhat like <hi>R. H.</hi> of a Legall Spirit, thinking the old Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall adminiſtration ſhould continue, and it may be ſtood ſomewhat prejudiced to the New-light, like him. But Jeſus Chriſt whoſe will was to have the glorious Goſpell and new Covenant, go forth with new, even Goſpell adminiſtrations like it ſelfe, forbad them their demand with utter diſlike of it, (although it will not ſatisfie many mens ſpirits to this day) and told them that the Son of man cauſe not to deſtroy, but to ſave mens lives.</p>
            <p>It followes, <hi>Page</hi> 5. <hi>Therefore</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>if any ſhall perſwade you to ſeparate from the people of God or Ordinances, &amp;c.</hi> Marke how he ſtill goes on in begging of queſtions, if he had proved who were the <hi>people of God,</hi> and which were the <hi>Ordinances of God,</hi> then we ſhould have been better able to juſtifie a ſeparation from him, as he from <hi>Rome,</hi> or to have renounced ſuch ſeparation if unlawfull, yet let him know there is a lawfull ſeparation, as well as unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as may appeare, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.9. <hi>When divers were hardened and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but ſpake evill of that way before the multitude, he depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from them, and ſeparated the Diſciples,</hi> ſo 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Come out from among them and be ye ſeparate, &amp;c.</hi> Elſe why doth he refuſe to worſhip God as the Papiſts do, but becauſe of their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Doctrine, and humane inventions.</p>
            <p>It followes; <hi>Likewiſe if any ſhall perſwade you from the publike Miniſtry, and from the Sacrament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Marke ſtill how he beggs queſtions, but let him be plaine, what Miniſtry and Sacraments he meanes, and prove them to be Gods, and done in Gods way, and he ſhall receive an anſwer: for from ſuch as are Gods, and adminiſtred in Gods way, we ſay the ſame as he doth.</p>
            <p>Againe, he mentions <hi>praying and giving of thanks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am perſwaded there no true Chriſtian ſo Atheiſticall, but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112173:8"/> doth as faithfully, and conſtantly acknowledge in theſe duties, as <hi>R.H.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next followes his queſtion, <hi>Page</hi> 5. <hi>May I be led with every one that brings Scripture?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His anſwer is <hi>No, for none are readier to bring Scripture then ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers,</hi> true, which may be the cauſe that <hi>R. H.</hi> brings Scriptures ſo oft, and gives the true ſenſe ſo ſeldome.</p>
            <p>Next followes his notes or difference, firſt, <hi>thoſe that are decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>will practice many things that they have no rule in Scripture for.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, it is very true, and this we can make appeare to <hi>R. H.</hi> that he himſelfe doth ſo, for, what warrant out of Scripture hath he for a Church of Chriſt made up of all the world, as if a worldly Sanctuary were ſtill Gods Ordinance, as if a typicall State were ſtil in being? what Scripture hath he for a worldly worſhip, and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Miniſtery? for, ſuch as the Church is, ſuch is the Miniſtery, and worſhip of it. 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.5. <hi>They are of the world, therefore ſpeake they of the world, and the world heareth them.</hi> Such practices deny Chriſt to be come in the fleſh. 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.3. for he would have all that are borne into the world Sons of God, whether they be new borne or no, whereas the Apoſtle ſaith plainly, not by our naturall birth, but by our new birth we become the Sons of God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26. <hi>Ye are all the Sons of God by faith in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But marke his firſt proofe; for his inſtance, is, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 13. where the young Prophet following the advice of the old Prophet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the command of God, was ſlaine. I ſuppoſe he here diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers notable ignorance; for the Prophet there doth not go on his meſſage by a Word ordinary and written, but by an immediate Word from God, and ſhould have been taken off not by a mediate word, and pretended, as was that of the old Prophet, nor by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but by the ſame immediate Word that ſet him on worke. Even as <hi>Abraham</hi> had the ſame immediate Word to ſtay his hand from killing <hi>Iſaac,</hi> that commanded him to do it. Now the Word written, rather warranted the Prophet to eate for his health, and forbad <hi>Abraham</hi> to kill, but they had a word immediately from the ſame fountaine from whence the Word written firſt came, which being written, is a record and rule to all the Saints; but it ſeemes <hi>R. H.</hi> would not have God himſelfe, nor the Prophets and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112173:8"/> Apoſtles in no caſe to goe a jot higher then the Word written.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Page</hi> 6. He mentions three or foure things negatively; the firſt is about Childrens Baptiſme, and ſome other things, queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what we have againſt them; and becauſe he thinkes nothing can be ſaid againſt that point, concerning the Baptiſme of water, let him take theſe few things into conſideration. Firſt, how he can warrant the baptizing of any with water by vertue of that commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Go teach all Nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> becauſe the Apoſtles themſelves that baptized with water before that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion was giuen, could not baptize with this Baptiſme, till they were indued with power from one high, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.49. <hi>Tarry ye in the City of Jeruſalem, till you be indued with power from on high, Acts</hi> 1.4. <hi>And being aſſembled together with them, commanded them that they ſhould not depart from Jeruſalem, but waite for the promiſe of the Father, which, ſaith he, ye have heard of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The baptiſme of water was ever, both before and after the giving of the Holy Ghoſt, called, <hi>Iohns Baptiſme, Act.</hi> 1.22. <hi>Beginning from the baptiſme of</hi> John, <hi>unto the ſame day that he was taken up from us, Acts</hi> 18.25, <hi>This man was inſtructed in the way of the Lord, and being fervent in the Spirit, he taught diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the things of the Lord, knowing only the baptiſme of Iohn.</hi> And <hi>Acts</hi> 19.3, 4, <hi>He ſaid unto them, unto what were ye then baptized! they ſaid, unto Iohns Baptiſme: then ſaid</hi> Paul John <hi>verily baptized with the baptiſme of repentance,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, And no other forme of words were uſed in that Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, but in the name of the Lord Jeſus only, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.16. <hi>For as yee the Holy Ghoſt was falne upon none of them only they were baptized in the name of the Lord Ieſus, Acts</hi> 19 5. <hi>When they heard this they were baptized in the name of the Lord Ieſus.</hi> For the baptiſme of the Spirit was by laying one of the Apoſtles hands, <hi>Acts.</hi> 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Then laid they their hands on them, and they received the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, The baptiſme of the Spirit was not ſo much as ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by the baptiſme with water as may appeare, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.2. <hi>And he ſaid unto them have ye received the Holy Ghoſt, ſince ye belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? and they ſaid unto him, we have not ſo much as heard whether there be any Holy Ghoſt;</hi> But if the Baptiſme of the ſpirit had been
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112173:9"/> the thing ſignified by the baptiſm with water, the Baptizers would no doubt have ſo inſtructed the parties baptized, or elſe they muſt be concluded to be either negligent or ignorant of their office: But <hi>Paul</hi> did not ſo much as reprove thoſe Baptizers for any ſuch neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, but by laying on of <hi>Pauls</hi> hands they received the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Nay further, This Baptiſme of the Holy Ghoſt was a diſtinct gift of the Spirit, from that which the Apoſtles and all other Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers receive by their union with Chriſt, for the Apoſtles had thoſe gifts and graces which were, and ſtill are common to other Beleevers, by vertue of their union before this was given; but this which is the <hi>promiſe of the Father,</hi> they had not till Chriſt was aſcended, <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.39. <hi>This he ſpake of the Spirit, which they that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve on him ſhould receive, for the Holy Ghoſt was not yet given becauſe that Ieſus was not yet glorified. Acts</hi> 1.5. <hi>Ye ſhall be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Holy Ghoſt not many daies hence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith expreſly it was no part of his commiſſion, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.15, 17. but the Baptiſme of the Spirit, by laying on of hands, was part of the Apoſtles commiſſion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. compared with <hi>Acts</hi> 8.18. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.15, 16, 17.</p>
            <p>If any object and ſay, what doth the Baptiſme with water ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie then?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, it ſignifies our remiſſion of ſins by the death of Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. <hi>Then ſaid</hi> Peter <hi>repent and be baptized every one of you in the name of Ieſus Chriſt for the remiſſion of ſins,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. And as for the ſubjects of this Baptiſme of water, I commend to <hi>R.H.</hi> his conſideration, Mr. <hi>Tombes</hi> his Book who is a Presbyterian (as they are called) and hath written largely upon that point, whoſe Book yet remaines unanſwered for any thing I underſtand to the contrary; &amp; when <hi>R.H.</hi> hath anſwered him rightly, he will ſatisfie many Chriſtians who are at a ſtand, and very much troubled about that point, and when he hath poſitively proved his other things he ſpeakes of, and turned his interrogations into poſitive concluſions fully proved, we ſhall then more particularly know what to anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to them: In the meane time, we will ſuffer him to make Quaerees, and becauſe he loves quaerees, let him take this one, not what he hath againſt, but what he hath for any of his way, to deſire of the Parliament that which is inconſiſtent to the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Laws of the Kingdome, did ever any of thoſe whom
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112173:9"/> he calls perverſe and obſtinate people deſire ſuch a thing. Let him alſo know, that untill he hath poſitively proved his own practice, he muſt be ſuſpected for a ſeducer, according to his own firſt rule: And marke further, how he ſwerves from his owne firſt rule, for whereas he titles thoſe, deceivers, that will practice that, they have no rule from Scripture for; he finding himſelfe deſtitute of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, runs to the old Popiſh ſhift, and makes Quaeries, and ſaith, what have you againſt ſuch and ſuch things, but let him know that God hath Interrogations to ſet againſt his Interrogations, which will overthrow them: <hi>Eſay</hi> 1.12. ſaying, <hi>Who hath required this at your hands:</hi> So that we have enough againſt a thing, when we have nothing for it; for poſitive poſitions and practices muſt have poſitive proofes, for negative poſitions, negative proofes ſuffice: I do not a thing, becauſe I find it not written, ſufficeth. Therefore the Jewes circumciſed Males becauſe there was expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for it, and not Females becauſe they found it not written, and yet they had no expreſſe command againſt it: So in the Law we read, that the Prieſts were to beare the <hi>Arke</hi> on their ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, <hi>Num.</hi> 4.15. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.2. as was there expreſly comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but there was no expreſſe command againſt carrying it on a Cart, only they had learned that of the <hi>Philiſtims:</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. but God made a breach upon them for it, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.8, 9. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.13. And ſo they learned to do it afterwards according to the Law of God: 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.14, 15. <hi>And the children of the Levites bare the</hi> Arke <hi>of God upon their ſhoulders, as</hi> Moſes <hi>commanded according to the Word of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He interrogates yet further, In <hi>Page</hi> 6. ſaying, <hi>what Scripture have any to raile againſt the Parliament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Truly, none that I know of, nor any warrant at all to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull toward them in the leaſt, who have been ſo carefull of our peace and ſafety, and ſo faithfull towards us, though ſome would have had it otherwiſe. But <hi>R. H.</hi> would make the world beleeve, that thoſe that differ from his opinions and practices are ſuch, and therefore mentions divers opinions, and among the reſt this Interrogatory, to render them as hatefull to the world as poſſibly he can, as this Interrogatory eſpecially muſt needs do if it were true; but it may be he hath heard ſome that ſtand oppoſite to his opinions, ſpeake fooliſhly that way, though for my part all thoſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112173:10"/> that I am intimate with, ſtand to this day as cordiall and reall for the Parliament as ever, as our neighbours can teſtifie: But contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, I have heard of ſome of his opinion that have proved un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull to the Parliament; ſhould I therefore take occaſion to make mention of the actions of ſome few of his opinion to the world, to render all of the ſame opinion odious? yet this is the very drift of his mentioning this thing, as may appeare to them that read his Booke. But it may be he will ſay he doth but inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate; but he may know well that interrogations are either ſtrong affirmations, or ſtrong negations; and I thinke he will not ſay it is a negation, but ſhould I have begun and done ſuch a thing ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely againſt them of his opinion, I ſhould have been thought at leaſt a ſeducer, unjuſtly endeavouring to draw the Parliament and well affected peoples affections from ſuch.</p>
            <p>His next things he mentions in the ſame page, are <hi>Magiſtrates, Maſters and Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Verily I know none that are accuſed by <hi>R. H.</hi> that take away in the leaſt from Parliament, Maſters or Fathers, what God, nature, and this whole Kingdome hath inveſted them with ſeverally from God; but I never yet read in the Goſpell of Chriſt Jeſus, that ever he gave any in the world power over the conſciences of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in matter of worſhip, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.23. <hi>Ye are bought with a price, be not the ſervants of men.</hi> Col. 2.20. <hi>Why as though living in the world, are ye ſubject to Ordinances; touch not, taſte not, handle not, which all periſh with the uſing after the Commandements and Doctrines of men:</hi> But marke the enmity of this man againſt them hee oppoſes hee would have them thought to bee ſuch as cry downe ſuperiority and inferiority, and yet he knowes well they ſtand for all due ſubjection to <hi>Caeſars,</hi> Maſters, and Fathers, as much as he, if not more: For we conceive all civill ſubjection to be due to ſuch, whether Heathens or Chriſtians; but if he will give to them that which belongs to God, we are not bound to doe ſo too by his example: we acknowledge no power in matter of worſhip above Chriſt Jeſus, who is the only Law-giver to his people, whoſe government differs from <hi>Moſes</hi> government, even as his houſe differs from his, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.2, 3, 4, 5, 6. who was faithfull to him that appointed him, as alſo <hi>Moſes</hi> was faithfull in all his houſe: <hi>And</hi> Moſes <hi>verily was faithfull in all his houſe as a ſervant, but
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112173:10"/> Chriſt as a ſonne over his own houſe, &amp;c.</hi> So that the Government of <hi>Moſes</hi> houſe is as unfit for Chriſts houſe, as a poore cottagers for a Kings houſe.</p>
            <p>Beſides <hi>Moſes</hi> houſe, yea, even that whoſe State being ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowiſh, when Chriſt the body came, the ſhaddowes muſt needs fly away, (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith) then to what purpoſe ſerve his proofes from the examples of the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> more then of the Prieſts of <hi>Judah,</hi> for the Government of Chriſts houſe; unleſſe they are underſtood ſpiritually and not according to the Letter: For were not the Kings and Prieſts of <hi>Judah,</hi> both types of Chriſt Jeſus? Now if he will more argue from the one than from the other, let him ſhew his grounds from Scripture; if he will argue from both, as he muſt of neceſſity if he do from either, then how wil he eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape the Epiſcopall order, even the Papall power of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, which they raiſe up to the foundation of the Aaronical Prieſthood.</p>
            <p>But it may be <hi>R. H.</hi> is not throughly convinced of the truth, and extent of the typicality of that eſtate, nor the ſpirituality of the preſent Goſpell ſtate as the antitype of that: Let him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a little conſider, firſt the Land is called holy, <hi>Zach.</hi> 2.12. <hi>The glory of all Lands, Ezek.</hi> 20.6. <hi>Emmanuels Land, Eſay</hi> 8.8. <hi>the typicall reſt, Deut.</hi> 12.9, 10. Which when men beleeve, they are ſaid to enter into, not that naturall <hi>Canaan,</hi> but the ſpirituall reſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.3. <hi>For we which have beleeved enter into reſt,</hi> &amp;c, Beſides, <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> when the Jewiſh ſtate ſtood, was the chiefeſt place of Gods worſhip, unto which all men of that Nation, were bound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort three times a yeare, according to the Law, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34, 23, 24. <hi>Thrice in the yeare ſhall all your men children appeare before the Lord.</hi> So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122. But now every where, and in every Nation men may worſhip God, if they worſhip him in Spirit and truth: <hi>John</hi> 4.20, 21, 23. <hi>The houre commeth when ye ſhall neither in this Mountaine, nor in Jeruſalem worſhip the Father, But the houre commeth and now is, when the true worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Spirit and truth. Acts</hi> 10 35. <hi>In every Nation he that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth him and worketh righteouſneſſe, is accepted of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The people were ſeparated from other people to God, <hi>Levit.</hi> 20.26. <hi>I the Lord am holy, and have ſevered you from other people that you ſhould be mine:</hi> But where hath God in the Goſpell ſeparated any whole Nation or Kingdome as a peculiar people,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:112173:11"/> but rather chuſeth out to himſelfe a people by the voyce of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, not of all Nations, but out of all Nations and tongues: <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Thou haſt redeemed us by thy bloud out of every kindred, and tongue, and people, and Nation.</hi> And is it not plaine, that the <hi>ſpirituall Iſrael, holy Nation, and peculiar people,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> calls them, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re the true Antitype of that?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Prieſthood was typicall, as may be ſeene at large, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7, 8, 9 Chapters, what was ſignified by it, and how, and in whom fulfilled.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, To go no further, though much more might be ſaid, the Kingdome of <hi>Judah</hi> was typicall to Chriſt according to that, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10. <hi>The Scepter ſhall not depart from</hi> Judah, <hi>nor a Law-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver from between his feet, till</hi> Shilo <hi>come.</hi> So <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 3, 5. <hi>Afterward the children of Iſrael ſhall returne and ſeeke the Lord their God, and</hi> David <hi>their King, and ſhall feare the Lord and his goodneſſe in the latter daies. Ezek.</hi> 37.22, 24, 25: <hi>And I will make them one Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and one King ſhall be King to them all:</hi> ver. 24. <hi>And</hi> David <hi>my ſervant ſhall be their King. Amos</hi> 9.11. <hi>In that day I will raiſe up the Tabernacle of</hi> David <hi>that is falne.</hi> So <hi>Eſay</hi> 9.6. <hi>Dan,</hi> 7. <hi>Joh,</hi> 1.49. <hi>Thou art the King of Iſrael:</hi> So <hi>Luke</hi> 1.32. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.30. and many more places. And which is more, the Law-giving power was ſo appropriated to <hi>Judahs</hi> Tribe, that it was common to none other in the world with him, and obſerve that this Law-giving power (I do not ſay Law-making power for that was wholy delivered to them from God: 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.11. to the end, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.25. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31.2, 3.) was ſo peculiar to <hi>Judahs</hi> Tribe, that it was not common, no not to the Kings of Iſrael, who were Chriſtian Kings by profeſſion, and lawfull by Gods approbation, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 11. elſe now were any Kings lawfull either in Iſrael or Judah? for God told them expreſly when they deſired a King firſt, that they had caſt him off, that he ſhould not raigne over them: 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.5, 6 7. But as Gods approbation of it afterwards made that lawfull, ſo alſo this, having alſo Gods approbation before the diviſion; 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.31, 37, 38. <hi>And he ſaid to</hi> Jeroboam, <hi>take thee ten pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for thus ſaith the Lord, I will rend the Kingdom out of the hands of</hi> Solomon, <hi>and give ten Tribes unto thee, and if thou harken to what I command thee, and keep my Statutes as</hi> David <hi>my ſervant did, I will be with thee, and build thee a ſure houſe, as I built for</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:112173:11"/> David, <hi>and will give Iſrael unto thee.</hi> Yet he never approved of their actions about his worſhip, for that as I ſaid, was peculiar to <hi>Judahs</hi> Tribe, yet, even this priviledge that was in <hi>Judahs</hi> Tribe, was no morall right, but typicall and ſhadowiſh only, and ſo was wholy to vaniſh away, and ceaſe for ever when Chriſt came. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 21.26, 27. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, remove the Diadem, and take off the Crowne, this ſhall not be the ſame, exalt him that is low, and abaſe him that is high, I will overturne, overturne, overturne it, and it ſhall be no more untill he come whoſe right it is, and I will give it him.</hi> Now no Civill Kings of the Nations of this world, were typed out, but Chriſt Jeſus only, from whom it is that all Beleevers in a ſpirituall reſpect are equally Kings and Prieſts. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6. for even as the Land, People and Prieſthood were types of a Spirituall, not Civill, Land, People and Prieſthood; even ſo their Kings muſt alſo have their Spirituall Antitypes, and ſo it followes clearly, not Civill but ſpirituall, even Chriſt Jeſus is the true Antitype ſhadowed forth, for if it were not ſo, the very eſſentiallity of types and figures would be taken away and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but the Civill power which is from nature, and ſo Morall and perpetuall continues ſtill, and ſubjection to it is expreſly comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Civill things, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14. whereas ſubjection to it in matters Spirituall, is as expreſly forbidden, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20 25, 26, 27, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.25, 26, 27. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.23. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.20, 22. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.9. And this is the true ſenſe of the Goſpell in this point, thus clearly diſtinguiſhing betwixt the Civill and Spirituall power.</p>
            <p>A little further he ſets the Scriptures at variance amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſo leaves them, never ſhewing what the ſpirit of God meanes in thoſe places of <hi>Jude</hi> 3. <hi>Contend earneſtly for the faith once given to the Saints;</hi> and <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. <hi>The Kingdome of Heaven ſuffers violence, and the violent take it by force.</hi> But he doth in this caſe, as ſome Fiſhes, who will make the water thick and mud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, that they may the eaſier get away undiſcerned; it may be he counteth all calling into queſtion his wayes to be contention, though it be done lovingly, and his open calumniating others that differ from him, to be no ſtriving nor contention, giving them his charitable brand, a perverſe and obſtinate people: But if this be his charity, we deſire he ſhould keep it to himſelfe, and pretend leſſe love, and intend more.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:112173:12"/>
            <p>In <hi>Page</hi> 7. his ſecond rule to try the ſpirits, is this: <hi>Thoſe moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or perſwaſions that are pleaſing to the fleſh, and take moſt with naturall men, are not from the ſpirit of God:</hi> His proofes are, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. <hi>For the fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit, and the ſpirit againſt the fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. Whereto I anſwer; Our wayes cannot pleaſe naturall men; for we declare to them, that untill they be borne againe, and beleeve in Chriſt, they are carnall ſtill, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. <hi>If any man have not the ſpirit of God, he is none of his.</hi> And ſo being not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, they cannot be true Church-members. But they admit all without exception, and is not that pleaſing to fleſh and bloud to have their carnall wayes, and yet be counted Gods children too, as is plaine by their communicating with them in their Church-priviledges? But let <hi>R. H.</hi> goe about to unchurch them, and take away that Religion that they ſeeme to have from them, and then he ſhall ſee plainly whether it will diſpleaſe fleſh and bloud, or no.</p>
            <p>It followes, <hi>page</hi> 7. <hi>What profit is it that we keep his Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Verily if <hi>R. H.</hi> have repented of any ſervice performed by him to God, that was not Gods, he hath done well, and I hope he will ſay the ſame by us doing the like; but if he meanes it of that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice that indeed is Gods, I know none that repents of any ſervice performed to God, unleſſe it be of their wants and weakneſſes in their performances &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It followes <hi>page</hi> 8. where he quotes a place out of <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.26. and once before <hi>Pag.</hi> 2. but his Reader may go ſeeke the true ſenſe, the words are theſe, <hi>Wherefore if they ſhall ſay to you he is in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> go not forth; behold he is in the ſecret chamber, beleeve it not, &amp;c.</hi> But what, doth he thinke, is meant by the <hi>deſert?</hi> where is it thinks he? Is it ſome wilderneſſe naturall where wild Beaſts inhabite? this is indeed a naturall conſtruction; or is it Spirituall? which verily is more likely, according to that, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. whither the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man fled for ſhelter, and was preſerved there rather by Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, than by vertue of any true outward Church-Office and Ordinance. For the outward Court was given to the Gentiles, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2. and the true viſible Miniſtry by Office was departed, and an earthly one ſucceeded all that time of the forty two moneths, <hi>Revel.</hi> 9.1. <hi>I ſaw a Star fall from heaven to the earth,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112173:12"/> and to him was given the key of the bottomleſſe pit.</hi> And in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2. it is ſaid, <hi>the outward Court was given to the Gentiles,</hi> and this is that departing foretold by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.3. <hi>That day ſhall not come except there come a falling away firſt, and that man of ſinne be revealed,</hi> ſee Acts 20.29. <hi>After my departing ſhall grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Wolves enter in among you not ſparing the flocke.</hi> And by our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.24, 25, 26. <hi>For there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Luke</hi> 17.21, 22, 23. So that the Saints being in their ſpirituall Babyloniſh captivity, no marvell that their ſtate was ſo confuſed; For as in Babylon of old there was confuſion of tongues, <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.4, 7, 9. and from that confuſion Babell tooke its name, <hi>verſe</hi> 9. ſo in this ſpirituall Babylon the Church of God came into confuſion looſing that Apoſtolicall and firſt order of the Goſpell: yea, and take notice that that gift of tongues was one of thoſe gifts, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. that in ſpirituall Babylon was againe confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; yet ſome enjoyment of God was even there to the Saints, though not according to the former way: But even as Iſraell of old was extraordinarily nouriſhed in their captivity in heathen Babylon, <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13, 14. (ſo in myſticall Babylon, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhall appeare) <hi>Then I ſaid unto him, what are theſe two Olive Trees upon the right ſide of the Candleſticke, and upon the left ſide thereof; and what are thoſe two Olive branches, which through the two golden pipes empty the golden oyle out of themſelves, and he ſaid theſe are the two annoynted ones, that ſtand by the Lord of the whole earth.</hi> (There is mention made but of one Candleſticke, becauſe their Church was Nationall) they were extraordinarily preſerved, for the pipes emptied the golden oyle out of themſelves, they could not be provided for in the ordinary way, as that place before quoted proves, and may further appeare by the reinveſting againe of the Prieſts after their Captivity, <hi>Ezra.</hi> 6.20. <hi>For the Priests and Levites were purified together, all of them were pure:</hi> compared with <hi>Zach.</hi> 3. all along that Chapter; for what needed a reſtoring where was no loſſe.</p>
            <p>Moreover, after ſome degree of reſtoring, ſome difference about the Prieſts Office could not be decided, till a Prieſt aroſe with <hi>Urim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> infallibly to determine it, <hi>Ezra.</hi> 2.62, 63. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 7.64, 65. <hi>The Tirſhatha ſaid unto them, that they ſhould not eate of the moſt holy things, till there ſtood up a Prieſt with Urim
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112173:13"/> and Thummim.</hi> Even ſo I ſay, in this myſticall <hi>Babylon,</hi> the two Candleſticks (called two, becauſe the eſtate under the Goſpell is Congregationall) were likewiſe extraordinarily nouriſhed: <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3, 4. <hi>I will give power to my two witneſſes, and they ſhall Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy a thouſand two hundred and threeſcore daies in ſacke-cloath:</hi> Theſe are <hi>the two Olive Trees, and the two Candleſticks ſtanding before the God of the earth.</hi> Yet alſo ſome communion among themſelves there was, it may be ſomewhat like that, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16. For elſe how could the enemies find them out to perſecute them? yet a perpetuall viſibility of a Church in that eſtate, all the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Divines are contrary to; as Mr <hi>Saltmarſh</hi> declares in his <hi>Divine Right of Presbytery,</hi> Pag. 2. And it is leſſe probable that they ſhould have a viſible Miniſtry, than a viſible Church, the Scriptures being ſo plaine againſt that of the Miniſtry, but rather for that of the Church (and it is well known, a Church may ſubſiſt, at leaſt for ſome time without Officers, though not ſo well) which induces me to thinke that thoſe Divines before ſpoken of, do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that viſibility of Church they ſpeake of, chiefly of a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility by true Officers and Ordinances, and my reaſon is, becauſe I find two Candleſticks, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3, 4. (and no ſtars but earthly ones) all the time of Antichriſts raigne, Prophecying, although it was in Sacke-cloath. Some light they had, as I ſaid before, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they lived by faith, according to that <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.4. <hi>The juſt ſhall live by faith, &amp;c.</hi> And witneſſed to the truth againſt Antichriſt: Now the viſibility of the Church taken in this latter ſenſe, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to be neither in the deſart, nor in the ſecret chamber (that is, the moſt retired aſſemblings of the Saints) for in neither of theſe is Chriſt enjoyed, but when the Lord Jeſus ſhall repaire theſe loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, it ſhall be like that lightening from Eaſt to Weſt, which ſhall be obvious to all his people, and put an end to theſe Ordinance Controverſies.</p>
            <p>It followes, In the ſame Page he quotes <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. <hi>Marke them which cauſe diviſions, and offences contrary to the Doctrine which you have learned, and avoid them:</hi> This is very good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell indeed, when it is rightly underſtood, but the Papiſts bring this place againſt the Proteſtants, and the Proteſtants againſt the Papiſts; the Biſhops bring it againſt the Non-conformiſts, and they againſt them; and <hi>R. H.</hi> he brings it againſt his oppoſites, and they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:112173:13"/> againſt him. But the queſtion is, how ſhall we know when it is rightly brought? I anſwer; when the Church of God is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored againe from under Antichriſt to that Primitive purity, and firſt patterne of Truth, and he that maketh uſe of this Scripture, is in a Church way, anſwering that patterne, and is infallibly aſſured of it; then he may infallibly make uſe of this place, and declare who they are that make diviſions: and this ſenſe the latter part of the words include; for he adds, <hi>Marke them that cauſe diviſions, contrary to the Doctrine that ye have learned,</hi> that is, <hi>of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> and not any other Doctrine whatſoever, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. <hi>The things which thou haſt heard of me, commit to faithfull men, that they may be able to teach others.</hi> Now if <hi>R. H.</hi> meanes them that cauſe diviſions from the firſt patterne of Truth, we agree with him that ſuch are diligently to be marked: But he doth not declare and prove from what Church it is meant, that this diviſion is to be underſtood of, whether Nationall, or Congregationall, Primitive, or ſince the Apoſtacy under Antichriſt, and ſo he contends to no purpoſe.</p>
            <p>It followes, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.37. and <hi>Marke</hi> 3.28. <hi>All ſins and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhall be forgiven to the Sons of men, but he that ſins againſt the Holy Ghoſt ſhall never be forgiven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is good counſell becauſe it comes from Chriſt; but who are the ſubjects this principally lookes upon we ſhall ſee anon: For moſt plaine it is, that it was directed to the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees that <hi>adulterous generation, Mat.</hi> 12.39. that could dance after no Muſicke but their owne pipes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.16, 17. that could learne no truths, but ſuch as were brought to them in their owne way, who being affraid that Jeſus Chriſt was come to overthrow their Church Conſtitutions and Traditions, and all their falſe waies, made Chriſt as odious as they could to all the Jewes by their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives (as <hi>R. H.</hi> endeavours to do us to the world) declaring that he was <hi>a glutton, a drunkard, a friend of wicked men, Mat.</hi> 11.19. yea, <hi>a conjurer,</hi> which occaſioned this ſpeech of our Saviour, which he quotes. Now theſe men being ſo bewitched to their humane inventions and Conſtitutions, would ſay any thing againſt Chriſt to make their owne cauſe ſeem good: Now whether we or our oppoſites, oppoſe Chriſt moſt in matter of humane Conſtitutions and Inventions in Gods Worſhip, we leave to all Chriſtians to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112173:14"/> judge, and ſo conſequently, whom that ſpeech of our Saviour moſt concernes.</p>
            <p>Next follow two Objections, <hi>Page</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>The firſt is this. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Try all things and keep that which is good.</hi> But if the Reader marke his anſwer, he ſhall find that he ſcarce gives leave to trye any thing, for feare there ſhould be evill in it; would he not have us try appearances of evill, whether they are ſo or no? Would he have us take all upon truſt that comes from them? Truly, I do not read that <hi>Paul</hi> made, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Try all things and keep that which is good,</hi> the Objection, and <hi>ver.</hi> 22. <hi>Abſtaine from all appearance of evill,</hi> the anſwer to the Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is <hi>R. H.</hi> his addition to the Scripture, to darken the ſenſe of it. But the Apoſtles mind is, as I conceive, to teach us, <hi>ver.</hi> 21. to take nothing upon truſt untried, and being tried and found good, to keep it; and being found to be evill, to avoid it wholly in all its degrees, even to the very appearance of evill.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Objection is this: <hi>But they teach many ſweet Truths.</hi> He anſwers, <hi>therein lies the more danger.</hi> Truly, I conceive the danger lies not in teaching ſweet Truths, much leſſe in teaching many ſweet Truths; but the danger lies in this, when men make not uſe of that duty and Chriſtian Liberty they have from the Word of Truth, to try all things, they heare, whereſoever, or by whomſoever, whether they are Truths or not: Which duty and Liberty is ſo much infringed by him in this his anſwer, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the amplification of his anſwer, <hi>Page</hi> 9. by a fabulous ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, as if he meant to drive men wholly from triall.</p>
            <p>The next Objection, <hi>Page</hi> 9. which being large, I referre to his Booke, where he ſaith, <hi>That we ſay the way to have their eyes ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned is to forſake their Antichriſtian Miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This we deny, and ſay quite contrary, the way to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake Antichriſtian Miniſters, is to have mens eyes firſt opened by Jeſus Chriſt; and whereas he ſaith in the words following, that <hi>his oppoſites would have them come and joyne with them in their meetings:</hi> This is his ſlander, who is ſo jealous of all mens waies but his owne, that he is unwilling to make a found triall, either of other mens waies or his owne, but takes things at the firſt hand, to diſgrace others, and boulſter his owne, and ſo his poſitions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill begged and not proved, he builds without a foundation.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:112173:14"/> The ſimilitude he alludes to, of <hi>Eves eating the forbidden fruit,</hi> will not ſerve his turne, for that was proved infallibly to be forbidden fruit, but he takes for granted, and hath not yet proved the waies he ſo reproaches to be forbidden fruit: therefore his anſwer is of no force, but muſt needs remaine the conceit of his own braine and miſ-applied.</p>
            <p>It followes, <hi>Page</hi> 10. where he brings in <hi>the Phariſees accuſing Chriſts Diſciples of ignorance, John</hi> 7.49. <hi>yet boaſting themſelves of their owne light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I have declared a little before, who are moſt ſicke of the Phariſees diſeaſe, and truely, this mentioned here by him, is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Symptome of their infection; for they were better verſed in the Lawes and Traditions of their Fathers, than in the Lawes of Chriſt, and ſo accuſed Chriſts Diſciples of ignorance, ſo that I grant it to be as he ſaith, of the Phariſees, and it is a very Epidemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call diſeaſe amongſt all of that kindred: but now to the triall of his application, to ſee if it doth not touch himſelfe moſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Did he when he writ and compoſed his calumniating Book, thinke with himſelfe that he knew nothing? If ſo, I wonder how he durſt ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to put it forth, ſo to publiſh his ignorance to the world? Alſo, if he were free from all boaſting of his knowledge, what was it that made him to dignifie his Booke with ſuch a high title as <hi>The True Guide?</hi> this I commit to any reaſonable mans conſideration, whether he thought he <hi>know nothing,</hi> and was freed from boaſting, according to his quoted place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.2. When he wrote and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed his Book with ſo high a Title, and according to his other quoted place, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.18. <hi>He that commendeth himſelfe is not approved, but he whom the Lord commendeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Saint <hi>Paul</hi> anſwers him fully, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.8. with <hi>Acts</hi> 9.5. They that know Chriſt will not perſecute and crucifie Chriſt in himſelfe, nor in his members.</p>
            <p>The next Objection he ſeems to anſwer is, <hi>Page</hi> 10. Object. <hi>but I cannot anſwer their arguments, they are ſo deep, muſt not I then be faine to yeeld unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He anſwers, <hi>by no meanes, &amp;c.</hi> See how reſolute this man is, the deepeſt arguments cannot move him; but marke his proofe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.26. A third time abuſed; for this abſence of Chriſt here ſpoken of, is a like abſence from all men upon earth, and ſo from
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112173:15"/> 
               <hi>R. H.</hi> as well as from others, whether it be underſtood of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall abſence, or of the abſence of him in the externall and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull adminiſtrations of his Kingdom, in both theſe ſenſes the Scripture ſpeakes of his abſence. For that of his perſon, ſee <hi>Acts.</hi> 1.11. <hi>This fame Jeſus which is taken up from you into heaven, ſhall ſo come in like manner as ye have ſeen him goe into heaven.</hi> For that of the adminiſtrations of his Kingdome, in the gifts of the Spirit, ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.28. <hi>Marke</hi> 9.1. <hi>There be ſome ſtanding here which ſhall not taſte of death, till they have ſeene the Son of man comming in his Kingdome:</hi> which abſence was ſupplied and enjoyed in the gifts of the Spirit, as I have declared before at large; as alſo, how this enjoyment was againe loſt under Antichriſt. Now he muſt of neceſſity underſtand that abſence of Chriſt in one of theſe two ſenſes, for it cannot be underſtood of an inward and ſpirituall abſence, for that enjoyment that ſlowes from union is perpetuall; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11. <hi>But if the Spirit of him that raiſed up Jeſus from the dead dwell in you, he that raiſed up Chriſt from the dead, ſhall quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken your mortall bodies by his Spirit that dwells in you.</hi> So 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Whoſoever is borne of God doth not commit ſin, for his ſeed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth in him, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe things being premiſed, it followes clearly, that we are forbidden to goe after <hi>R. H.</hi> into the deſert to ſeeke Chriſt, or after others into the ſecret Chambers, he being alike abſent from all, untill that in <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.27, 28. be fulfilled, <hi>For as the lightning commeth out of the Eaſt, and ſhineth into the Weſt, ſo ſhall the comming of the Son of man be, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe things I thought good to adde to that ſpoken of before, to make the matter more plaine.</p>
            <p>It followes, he ſaith, <hi>The Spirit of God bids remember how thou haſt received, and heard, and hold faſt and repent: Rev.</hi> 3.3. Very good counſell to him and us, and it is very well backed with two other proofes, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Hold faſt the forme of ſound words. Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9. <hi>Thogh we or an Angell from heaven preach any other Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell to you then this, let him be accurſed.</hi> Where we finde, that no Aſſemblies or Churches in the world muſt be our rule, but only the true patterne of wholſome words; here <hi>R. H.</hi> ſeemes as if he would keepe to the patterne, and if it were ſo, why is he ſo angry with us for ſo doing? We dare not do any thing without Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as he doth, as we have already declared, and ſhall further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112173:15"/> in the matter following: And whereas he mentions <hi>Thiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rahs</hi> Propheteſſe that came with her deep learning, I underſtand that to be ſo, becauſe ſhe ſpake not as <hi>the Oracles of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.11. <hi>But with the enticing words of mans wiſdome:</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4. And where hath <hi>R H.</hi> had either by word or writing, ſuch from his op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites, except a paſſage or two in this our anſwer, to pay him in his owne Coyne, for we have had ſuch from his Epiſtle, as <hi>Orthodox, Heterodoxe, Enthuſiaſmes, Ignis fatnus, Anodines, Enchiridion.</hi> If he call this deepe learning, we agree with him; but if he meane by deep learning, that which is allowed of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. &amp; ſuch as our arguments to him have hitherto beene, and ſtill do conſiſt of, then it is no marveile he cannot anſwer them; for God ſaith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, that ſuch as are reſolved and ſetled in their formall waies, ſetting up that Idoll in their hearts, they ſhall not have the Truth diſcovered to them, but he will in judgement being enquired of, ſuffer the Word to ſound after the ſenſe of their old formes, and falſe wayes, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.4. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God, every man of the houſe of Iſrael, that ſetteth up his Idols in his heart, and putteth the ſtumbling blocke of his iniquity before his face, and commeth to the Prophet to enquire of him concerning me, I the Lord will anſwer him according to the multitude of his Idols.</hi> But truly, his learning in his Booke is ſhallow enough, for it hath no ground or foundation whereon to build that he chiefly aimes at, and what that is, I have declared already.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Page</hi> 11. I find a pretended anſwer, to a pretended allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which he there ſaith he met with, how true I know not, it is this; <hi>They perſwade people, that the Word delivered in private, and by private men of their way, is more ſweet, and they can profit more by it, than by that which is taught in the publike Miniſtry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which he gives a twofold anſwer: firſt, he makes that had in a private way, to be <hi>ſtolne waters, Pro.</hi> 9.17. and <hi>forbidden fruit, Gen.</hi> 2.9, 16, 17. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.6. Whereto I anſwer; firſt, if ours be <hi>ſtolne waters,</hi> ſo is his, for he preaches in private (take private in his own ſenſe) as I have declared before, and I wonder how he dares to trade in <hi>ſtolne waters,</hi> and to eate <hi>forbidden fruit,</hi> unleſſe it be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for him only ſo to preach, and not for others.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, though he hath overthrowne his own practice, he hath not yet proved our practice to be either <hi>ſtolne waters,</hi> or
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:112173:16"/> 
               <hi>forbidden fruit,</hi> as I have declared already upon another the like occaſion, whereto I referre.</p>
            <p>And whereas in <hi>Page</hi> 11. he is large in his amplification of this to upbraid others, the matter there being convertible, it fits <hi>R. H.</hi> himſelfe, as much as it can do us, unleſſe he thinkes that we are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bound to have and ſhew love towards him, and he quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary towards us; verily in this, he deales juſt like the Phariſees, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. require much from others, but performe little themſelves. So he would have all our words and waies towards him, paved with butter and hony, though his words and waies, be with gall and wormewood towards us, as by and by ſhall appeare.</p>
            <p>His next allegation he ſeemes to anſwer, is in the ſame <hi>Pag.</hi> 11. and it is this, <hi>They would perſwade people, that we are not able to maintaine what we teach or hold, for they have offered to reaſon with our Miniſters, or private men, but they cannot get us to it,</hi> (this he knows for the moſt part to be true) but he anſwers, <hi>ſome of you have been reaſoned with, and confuted too, though you will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it; but if any have refuſed, it is not becauſe we cannot maintaine the Truth we hold, but becauſe you are a perverſe people, that will not yeeld to the true meaning of the Spirit of God in the Scriptures, but will make all Scriptures to ſpeake what they would have them ſpeake, to maintaine what they hold and practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer; firſt, he acknowledges in part, our readineſſe to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with them, and their unwillingneſſe to reaſon with us: But whereas he ſaith further, that we have been reaſoned with, and confuted too, he ſhould have done well to have declared in what particulars, the time when, and the place where, and in the meane time we muſt taxe him for an untruth.</p>
            <p>It follows, <hi>Page</hi> 12. where he ſaith, <hi>Becauſe you are a perverſe people, and perverſe and obſtinate in an erronious way, ſuch as will heare no reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In <hi>Pag</hi> 11. in the laſt amplification, he cenſures the cenſorious, that they do not indeed profit by the Word, becauſe they grow not in charity; and ſo by his owne Doctrine he profits, not by the Word in their Aſſemblies, becauſe he is not charitable, but very cenſorious, doing that which the Word plainly forbids, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.1, 2, 3. <hi>Judge not that ye be not judged, for with what judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ye judge, ye ſhall be judged, and with what meaſure you mete, it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:112173:16"/> ſhall be meaſured to you againe; And why beholdeſt thou the moate that is in thy brothers eye, but conſidereſt not the beame that is in thine owne eye, &amp;c.</hi> Rom. 14.4. <hi>Who are thou that judgeſt another mans ſervant, to his own maſter he ſtands or falleth.</hi> Chriſt Jeſus is our maſter to whom we ſtand or fall, therefore let not <hi>R. H.</hi> be ſo proud, as to get into our Maſters Chaire, for he will queſtion him for ſo doing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.10. <hi>Why doſt thou judge thy brother, or why doſt thou ſet at naught thy brother, we ſhall all appear before the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeat of Chriſt:</hi> If <hi>R. H.</hi> had cenſured us to be falſe worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, in relation to ſome outward falſe worſhip, it might have ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued rather weakneſſe than wickedneſſe in us, and ſo ſome place left for charity, that we might have been Chriſtians ſtill: But he hath point blanke made us Hereticks (according to the common and known diſtinction of Hereſie that obſtinacy joyned with error is Hereſie) yea, a little more vile too, even brutiſh, ſuch as will heare no reaſon, and yet for all this, he would be thought to be humble, and charitable.</p>
            <p>Further ſaith he, <hi>You are a perverſe people, that will not yeeld to the true meaning of the Spirit of God in, the Scriptures, but will make all Scriptures ſpeake what they would have them ſpeake, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Truly, we do no more feare his falſe cenſures here, than his falſe Engliſh; but the truth is, that he takes for granted, that only to be the true meaning of the Spirit of God in the Scripture, which he yeelds to: And all that differ from him, to be a perverſe people, ſo that many thouſands who are as really godly as ever was <hi>R. H.</hi> come under this cenſure and are by him made Hereticks: But if it be ſo, that he himſelfe uſeth to make all Scriptures ſpeake what he would have them ſpeake: let him not conclude others do ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he doth ſo, but let him remember his owne leſſon, and learne it, <hi>Page</hi> 11. he ſaith there. <hi>They that profit by the Word, are more humble and low in their owne eyes, and thinke every Chriſts<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>then themſelves: Phil.</hi> 2.3. <hi>and that at here know more of God then they do,</hi> as <hi>Elihu, Job</hi> 32.6. <hi>Who ſaith I am young and ye are old, wherefore I was affraid, and durſt not ſhew you mine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> But ſeeing <hi>R. H.</hi> hath firſt ſpoken and publiſhed his opinion, and that in a rigid and cenſorious way. I am induced to take <hi>Elihu's</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther counſell, <hi>verſe</hi> 9.10. where he ſaith, <hi>Great men are not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wiſe, neither do the aged underſtand judgement, therefore I ſaid
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:112173:17"/> hearken to me, I will alſo ſhew you my opinion:</hi> And ſo may I to <hi>R.H.</hi> though he be ſomewhat more aged then I, declare my opinion, for poſſibly <hi>R.H.</hi> may erre, he is not a man infallible, he may pervert the Scriptures as well as another man, and ſo be liable to tryall, unleſſe it be lawfull for him to Stigmatize others without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troule.</p>
            <p>A little further, in <hi>Page</hi> 12. he ſaith, <hi>Some of them have denyed the truth of ſome Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This one expreſſion, the truth of ſome Scriptures plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declares who he meanes, as ſhall by and by appeare; and verily, had he been charitable and not malicious, he would not have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned this about the Scriptures, it being openly among all our op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites, (at that meeting where the difference about ſome Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures aroſe) agreed upon, as all can witneſſe that were then preſent, and this it was, it was about <hi>Jobs</hi> three friends that came to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit him, and I then ſpake to this effect, that though the ſpeech of <hi>Jobs</hi> three friends was in the Scripture, and was a true relation of it, and ſo in that ſenſe is Scripture, ye it is not poſitively the truth and mind of God, as it came from them in relation to God &amp; <hi>Job,</hi> and ſo in this latter ſenſe, it is not the Scripture, Word or Truth of God: my reaſons are not only becauſe <hi>Job</hi> diſclaimes their ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, but even God himſelfe, <hi>Job.</hi> 42.7, 8. <hi>Saying, ye have not ſpoken of me the thing that is right.</hi> Now if it be not right, it is falſhood, and ſo none of Gods Truth, but only in the ſenſe afore ſaid, that is to ſay, a true relation.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But you are not the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> meant in the True Guide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Truly, I wonder how he dares in the leaſt to deny it, the things being ſo plainly ſpoken, which for the greateſt part have paſſed betwixt us in this place, from <hi>Page</hi> 11. <hi>the foure laſt lines, and almoſt halfe way in Page</hi> 12. but eſpecially this, about denying the truth of ſome Scriptures: I heare indeed, a rumour of ſome men in the world that deny the Scriptures, but they deny all alike, and not ſome only, and ſo cannot be the parties here intended, for thoſe intended here deny but ſome only. Beſides, I ſent him word by a friend of his, that if we were none of them he aimed at in his Booke, if he would but cleare us by declaring who they were, it might give ſatisfaction to us, but we have no anſwer to this day, therefore it is plaine to me and others, that all his faire gloſſes,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112173:17"/> and guilded ſhewes to the contrary, were but figg leaves to delude us, that he might render us odious unobſerved, and this his cunning evaſion, is but a new tricke of the old Serpent, to deceive us by faire words and foule deeds: but let him read that place, <hi>Rev</hi> 9.7, 8 and conſider it well, thoſe <hi>Locuſts</hi> there ſpoken of, are ſaid to have <hi>faces as the faces of men,</hi> reaſonable and modeſt in their words and outward appearance, but they had <hi>teeth like Lyons</hi> to bite withall: And I am perſwaded that the new perſecution of the Saints that is to come by the old formall Profeſſours, ſhall be moſt bitter; for who were greater enemies and perſecutors of Chriſt and his Diſciples, then thoſe formall Profeſſors the Phariſees, who were the ſtricteſt in the Jewiſh Religion, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.4, 5. even as thoſe who were formerly called Puritans in the Proteſtant Religion: Yet I ſpeake not this of all that are our oppoſites in judgement, for I put a wide difference betwixt thoſe whom God hath endewed with the Spirit of brotherly love and concord, and thoſe who remaine ſtill bewitched with the Antichriſtian ſpirit of perſecution.</p>
            <p>But it may be <hi>R. H.</hi> will ſay, you plead for Chriſtian Liberty, and will not ſuffer us to enjoy ours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If <hi>R. H.</hi> ſay, his Chriſtian liberty conſiſts in perſecuting his brethren, who are as deare to Chriſt as himſelfe, I utterly deny ſuch Chriſtian liberty both in judgement and practice, and deſire him to cleare and prove that to be lawfull which he hath done al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready; namely, to publiſh the grievances and differences among the Saints to the world, contrary to that of <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.20. except he thinke that God as little regards the credit of his people as he; or leſſe now then in the time of the Law: Certaine it is, that God will have a time to vindicate his peoples reproach, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Behold ſaith the Lord, at that time I will undee all that afflict thee, &amp;c. And I will get them praiſe and fame in every Land where they have been put to ſhame:</hi> and <hi>ver.</hi> 10. <hi>I will make you a name and a praiſe among all people of the earth, when I turne backe your captivity, &amp;c.</hi> Truly, Gods people are yet in their Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall captivity, reproached not only from the world, but even of them who thinke themſelves no ſmall Chriſtians. And becauſe <hi>R.H.</hi> cites <hi>Doctor Sibbs</hi> on the <hi>Canticles,</hi> I alſo deſire him and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to read his notes upon thoſe words <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.7, <hi>Page</hi> 298. who in thoſe times he lived in, was not altogether unſenſible of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:112173:18"/> Gods people found then, even as we find now abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as if that Propheſie in <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.7. were now fulfilling. I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver it in his own words at large: <hi>It ſhould teach us,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>not to thinke the worſe of any for the differences of the times; the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> (that is, <hi>the Miniſters,</hi> as he interprets it) <hi>here take away the vaile of the Church, and her forwardneſſe is diſgraced by them.</hi> And is it not ſo now? are not our waies accounted mad zeale &amp; whim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeys, and doth not <hi>R.H.</hi> call it new light? dealing with us as thoſe did with Saint <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 17.19, 20. <hi>May we know what this new Doctrine whereof thou ſpeakeſt is? for thou bringeſt certaine ſtrange things to our eares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doctor <hi>Sibbs</hi> ſaith further, <hi>Take heed therefore we entertaine not raſh conceits of others upon the entertainment they find abroad in the world, or even among thoſe that have a ſtanding in the Church, for ſo we ſhall condemne Chriſt himſelfe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>how was he judged of the Prieſts, Scribes and Phariſees in his time?</hi> and this hath been the lot of the Church in all ages, the true members thereof were called Hereticke and Schiſmaticks; and is it not a matter of great zeale at this day, for many Miniſters to raiſe at Gods people, and call them <hi>Antinomians, Anabaptiſts, Separatiſts,</hi> &amp;c. and ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull tearmes to render them odious? Therefore ſaith Doctor <hi>Sibbs</hi> further, <hi>It is the poyſinfull pride of mans heart, when it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not raiſe it ſelfe by its man worth, it will endeavour to raiſe it ſelfe by the ruine of others credit, through lying ſlanders.</hi> The Devill was firſt a ſlanderer, and lyer, and then a murtherer; he cannot murther, except he ſlander firſt, even as thoſe that kill a Dogge, make the world beleeve that he was mad firſt, ſo they alwaies take away the credit of the faithfull in the world, and then perſecute them, and ſo thoſe watchmen that ſhould encourage the godly, they ſmite and wound them. To conclude, were it not for the juſt vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the Truth of our ſelves and others, I would never have put Pen to Paper, but he hath compelled me, as <hi>Paul</hi> was in a like caſe by the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> to his juſt vindication, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11. ſaith he, <hi>I am become a foole in glorying, ye have compelled me for I ought to have been commended of you:</hi> And ſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> was faine to goe contrary to <hi>Solomon</hi> counſell, <hi>Pro.</hi> 27.2. and praiſe himſelfe, to vindicate both the Truth and himſelfe.</p>
            <p>A little further in <hi>Pag.</hi> 22. he ſaith, <hi>They much deſire and pray for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:112173:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I beleeve his deſires and prayers are rather that we ſhould returne to them and their waies, then to Chriſt; but certaine it is, if he do pray for us, either his praying for us will make him ceaſe perſecuting of us, or his perſecuting will make him ceaſe praying for us.</p>
            <p>He ſaith, <hi>We further object, and bring many Scriptures to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade people to ſtand faſt in the Truth they have been taught, but they have not been taught the Truth, but have been taught a falſe and blind way by your Miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He anſwers, <hi>It is a very falſe and ſcandalous imputation caſt upon the faithfull Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, for have they not taught us Jeſus Chriſt, that we are freely juſtified and ſaved by him alone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer here, firſt <hi>R. H.</hi> labours to vindicate his faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters about their Doctrine; It is very well I ſay, if they do teach free Juſtification and Salvation by Chriſt alone: I can remember the time, ſince it was a rare thing to heare free-grace preached, eſpecially in the practicall part of Divinity. I my ſelfe have heard delivered in <hi>London</hi> not long ſince at a Faſt, that true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and humiliation, was able to remove Gods judgements, which if it be ſo, I marvell to what purpoſe Chriſt ſerves for? and one even of <hi>R. H.</hi> his intimate companions, is not very well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in that point, for I have heard him ſay divers times not long ſince, that the more good workes he did, the greater glory he ſhould have at laſt in Heaven, ſo laying the height of his glory on the foundation of his good workes, building this Babell on <hi>Nehe.</hi> 13.14. ſo that he may thank his good workes at leaſt, for the height of his glory. But I would deſire them to ſhew me what meaſure of glory is given freely, without any reſpect to workes, and what glory is intailed to workes? But ſuppoſe it be granted they teach Jeſus Chriſt more purely than formerly, yet I have obſerved, that the men that were as he Goats, in the Doctrine of Gods free grace and love, were as odious at the firſt, as ever <hi>Martin Luther</hi> was in his time, yea, and ſtill are too, many that remaine of <hi>R. H.</hi> his mind, for he doth what he can to diſgrace the teachers of it, ſtill by his Calumniations, as may plainly appeare in his Booke <hi>Pag.</hi> 9. and they can hardly forbeare bringing in <hi>Moſes</hi> Law of workes, in <hi>Moſes</hi> way of adminiſtration, whereas we are only under the Law
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:112173:19"/> to Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.21. If it were not ſo, why do they ſo raile againſt Gods people, under the name of <hi>Antinomians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſaith, <hi>We object and ſay your Miniſters are Antichriſtian, for they were called by an Antichristian power, there fore it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to heare them.</hi> He anſwers, <hi>that muſt be proved firſt which you ſay, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, had <hi>R. H.</hi> been indeed but a <hi>True Guide,</hi> he would have been punctuall in proving this point eſpecially, it being the chiefe point in difference betwixt us, and the maine thing he aimes at in his Book, as I ſaid in the beginning; but certaine it is, the man was at a ſtand here, and was faine to be of a good beliefe, and take things upon truſt, and would have others do ſo too; but obſerve the way he takes to prove the point, and to anſwer the objection; he goes foure wayes, and all wrong, for he brings not one proofe of Scripture poſitively to prove his Miniſters law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. But</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>He puts us upon negative proofes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>He compares them with other teachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>By two fabulous ſimilitudes of a Cooke and a Clarke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>By anſwering three queſtions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that here is not one rule from Scripture to prove it, and ſo he makes himſelfe a ſeducer, in his firſt anſwer to the laſt queſtion, <hi>Page</hi> 5. of his Booke Wherefore I anſwer: To the firſt of his foure things I have in a ſenſe anſwered already, by declaring the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a mans proving his practice poſitively by Scripture, which holds forth a rule for all lawfull practice, and not to require nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive proofes from others, for that is not Gods way.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond thing, where he compares them with other Teachers, I ſuppoſe he meanes Teachers by vertue of Office, and ſo we have none of any higher calling then <hi>R. H.</hi> when he himſelfe teaches; but if he will rightly compare his Miniſters, to find whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are Miniſters of Chriſt, or of Antichriſt, let him go to Scripture-patterne for all inward and outward qualifications for Chriſts Miniſters or Paſtors, according to that, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20. <hi>To the Law and to the Teſtimony, if they walke not according to this rule, it is becauſe there is no light in them:</hi> For what the Prophet ſaith of ſpeaking, I may ſay of practice: and 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.24. <hi>Let that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore abide in you</hi> (to be practiſed certainly) <hi>which ye have heard
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:112173:19"/> from the beginning, if that abide in you which ye have heard from the beginning, ye ſhall continue in the Son, and in the Father;</hi> now this is a way without exception.</p>
            <p>To his third thing, verily one ſimilitude hath as much authority as another; therefore conſider, that as it is not lawfull for any perſon without commiſſion and authority from the King, to uſe and apply the Kings Seale to convey any aſſurance in worldly matters, even ſo it is not lawfull for any man having no calling or commiſſion from Chriſt, to take upon him the adminiſtration of ſuch Ordinances of Chriſt, that never were adminiſtred by any without ſuch calling and commiſſion from Chriſt.</p>
            <p>To his fourth, which is by asking three queſtions, to which I anſwer by asking them other queſtions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, whether the inward call without the outward be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent? or whether God joyned not the inward and outward toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make it a ſufficient call?</p>
            <p>Secondly, Whether God allow of any calling beſides his own, whether inward or outward? and whether either of theſe allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of by God, being corrupted, whether then it be Gods or no?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Whether there be any difference betwixt a man that hath a corrupt calling to an Office not warranted by God, and a man that hath no calling to an Office? but ſuppoſe he that hath a corrupt calling, and he that hath no calling, ſhould preach by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of a true calling before they have it, ſhould I be guiltleſſe, and yet conſtantly by my preſence and practice allow of that which God allowes not of? ſhould not I be guilty of all corrupt Officers ſtanding ever ſince the time of Antichriſt? and ſo come under that Sentence of Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.48. <hi>Truly ſaith he, ye beare witneſſe that ye allow the deeds of your Fathers:</hi> and doth not <hi>a litle leaven leaven the whole lump,</hi> being unpurged, 1 Cor. 5 6, 7. or may ſome corruption be let alone unpurged, or may we in ſome things be guilty of allowing the deeds of our Fathers, and not in others?</p>
            <p>To conclude, If men may remaine lawfull Miniſters, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their corrupt calling from men, and cannot as <hi>R. H.</hi> ſaith, corrupt the Word of God? Whether are not they lawfull Miniſters that have their calling in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo may lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be heard?</p>
            <p>But marke how he reaſons; <hi>Why,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>were not</hi> Martin
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:112173:20"/> Luthers <hi>workes rejected but embraced.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Why? muſt <hi>R. H.</hi> needs be allowed a true Miniſter of thoſe that embrace his Booke? Do but take notice here how he alſo labours to juſtifie the Popiſh calling which I made mention of, for <hi>Luther</hi> had his outward calling there.</p>
            <p>Next he brings in <hi>Balaam</hi> a falſe Prophet, to prove a true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, <hi>Num.</hi> 23.21. but as <hi>Balaams</hi> ſpeaking ſome truths from the mouth of the Lord made him not a true Prophet, even ſo many truths delivered by others, doth not make them true Miniſters; for <hi>Balaam</hi> had as good and better will to curſe than to bleſſe Gods people, he was very deſirous to make them miſerable for filthy lucres ſake, even as there be many in theſe daies too like <hi>Balaam</hi> in this, witneſſe their railing Bookes and Sermons againſt Gods people, as if they were unwilling they ſhould live in the world by them, but it is but the old Antichriſtian practice. <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.17.</p>
            <p>In his <hi>laſt Page</hi> he pleads earneſtly for, and encourages people to the Miniſtry of the Word, and ſo do I alſo, but that is not the difference betwixt us; but our difference lies here; he would have people beleeve the true Miniſtery to be no where elſe, but with them in their way, as if they only had this <hi>open doores</hi> he ſpeaks of, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.8, 10.11.12. (he leaves out the 9. <hi>verſe,</hi> for feare it would have beat hard upon his quarters) but certainly the <hi>Word of God</hi> in the publike Miniſtry, as he calls it, neither <hi>came to them only, nor from them only,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.36. Beſides, he muſt firſt prove his Church and Miniſtry to be the <hi>Philadelphian State,</hi> before he lay claime to <hi>the open doore,</hi> for that is the <hi>Philadelphian</hi> Churches promiſe, for each Church had its peculiar promiſe, as may be ſeene, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2, 3. <hi>Chapters.</hi> And truly, I conceive <hi>R. H.</hi> to be yet a ſtranger to the glory of this <hi>Philadelphian State,</hi> but I deſire that both he and I may ſee the right ſenſe of that place, who they are that God hath or ſhall betruſt with that <hi>open doore,</hi> but ſure I am, it is <hi>a doore</hi> to the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and not the old, nationall, earthly one.</p>
            <p>Theſe things I thought good to returne in anſwer to <hi>R. H.</hi> his <hi>True Guide,</hi> in the behalfe of our ſelves and others, for our juſt vindication, and deſire the Lord to indue him, and the reſt of our oppoſites, with the ſpirit of Chriſtian wiſdome, moderation, and peace, and for this purpoſe let them mind that experimented Counſell of <hi>Gamaliel, Acts</hi> 5.35. <hi>Take heed to your ſelves what
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:112173:20"/> ye intend to do as touching theſe men,</hi> and ſo <hi>ver.</hi> 38, 39. <hi>Refraine from theſe men and let them alone, for if this Counſell or worke be of men, it will come to nought, but if it be of God, ye cannot overthrow it, leaſt happily ye be found even to fight againſt God:</hi> Let them I ſay, conſider theſe things, that ſo we may live at peace by them, and they by us, untill the God of peace, truth and love draw up all the Saints to himſelfe, in him who is truth it ſelfe, the Lord Jeſus, by a fuller making out of Truth ſo long obſcured, that ſo we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one in Truth, and in the meane time one in peace and love; and this ſhall be the conſtant deſire of him, who earneſtly follows after the enjoyment of Peace, Truth and Love, in one Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
